Guide to the Records of the National Jewish Welfare Board, undated, 1889-1995 (bulk 1917-1990) *I-337
American Jewish Historical Society, Newton Centre, MA and New York, NY
- Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers, undated, 1904-1995 (bulk 1920-1980); 919 linear feet.
  - Series A: Program Services, 1904-1989 (bulk 1930-1980); 234.46 linear feet.
    - Subseries 1: Camping Services, 1941-1988; 38 linear feet.
      This material documents the activities of JWB's camping services program, which provided consultation services to Jewish communal camps; assisted Federations and JCCs in providing proper camping facilities and effective programs; enhanced Jewish educational and cultural aspects of camping programs; conducted camping institutes; and cooperated with other national organizations in raising communal camping standards and in enriching Jewish camping.4 Day camping was first introduced to the center field by JWB in 1932 and though the camping program was originally focused on children, it grew to include older individuals as well, including the elderly and physically handicapped.5 JWB believed that "Jewish camps make a unique contribution to the welfare of the organized Jewish community. To a great extent camps, both resident and day, provide a totality of experiences which are not available anywhere else in the Jewish community... Camps provide an experience in democratic living and identification with the values of American society..."6
      This subseries provides a look at various aspects of the camping program, such as JWB's involvement with the National Conference on Jewish Camping (in Alfred Dobrof's files), and assistance provided by JWB to Jewish camps. Topics featured in Sherwood Epstein's files include design and structure of camps, and analysis of Jewish populations. The subseries also documents JWB's Shlichim and Uplan programs, whereby Israelis came to the U.S. to serve at JCC and Federation camps, while American high school students traveled to Israel. (Material on this can be found in Roslyn Kriegsfeld's files, as well as in the Leonard Rubin and Shlichim Program files.) In addition, the subseries includes analyses of JCC and YM-YWHA programs and operations, as they relate to camping services, field reports describing visits to camps, and scholarship grants, which document individuals selected to be camp counselors. (These files include photographs of the applicants.) Statements of purpose of various JCCs can also be found in Arthur Brodkin's files, as can studies and surveys related to camping. Materials consist of reports, studies, bylaws, surveys, brochures, budgets, lists, clippings, forms, pamphlets, proposals, procedures, speeches, agendas, constitutions, articles, manuals, resumes, minutes, correspondence, applications, questionnaires, photographs, and reel-to-reel tapes, which can be found in the Audio-Visual Materials subgroup.
      4 "National Jewish Welfare Board Establishes Camping Department: Alfred Dobrof Named Director of JWB's Camping Services, and Roslyn Kriegsfeld is Named Camping Consultant," December 1, 1972, I-337, NJWB, American Jewish Historical Society.
      5 Postal, Bernard. 1966. Change and Challenge: The Past Twenty Years of JWB's History. p. 71. In Change and Challenge: A History of 50 Years of JWB. Janowsky, Oscar I., Louis Kraft, and Postal, Bernard. New York: National Jewish Welfare Board.
      6 "Proposed Statement on JWB Camping Services," Leonard Rubin, undated, National Jewish Welfare Board, I-337, American Jewish Historical Society
      Related Materials: Subgroup I: Jewish Community Centers/Series A: Program Services/Subseries 3: Health and Physical Education.
    - Subseries 2: Florence G. Heller Research Center, 1959-1989; 8 linear feet.
      This series is divided into the following subsubseries: S. Morton Altman (1971-1975), Decision Making Survey (undated), General Files (1959-1989), Greater Washington Membership Survey (undated), Jewish Center Leadership Questionnaire (1988), JWB Research and Statistics (1973-1983), and Survey of Professionals Employed in the JCC Field (1989). Arranged alphabetically, geographically, and numerically.
      The Florence G. Heller - JWB Research Center was established in 1963 in cooperation with the National Association of Jewish Center Workers. Its function was to identify relevant problems which could be aided by research, and to design and implement effective research projects.7 In 1971 the Research Center was reestablished with a new focus, making the Center's main priority assisting JCCs and Ys in achieving their objectives.8
      This material includes the files of S. Morton Altman, who became Associate Director of the Center in 1973, and served as Director from 1974 to 1976. Topics covered here include summer programs at JCCs and camping surveys. The General files include material documenting the creation of the research center, as well as budget and financial material, proposed projects, and reports and studies on various topics. A variety of surveys are also included here, such as the Greater Washington Membership survey, which examined the JCC's image and the quality and value of JCC activities. Other materials include reports, correspondence, proposals, minutes, agenda, questionnaires, studies, and photographs, which are located in the Audio-Visual Materials Subgroup.
      7 Research Center Voted by Board of Directors. JWB Circle, February 1963. Page 1
      8 Florence G. Heller - JWB Research Center Summary of Research Activities, 1972-1973, undated, I-337, NJWB, American Jewish Historical Society
    - Subseries 3: Health and Physical Education, 1948-1981; 27.75 linear feet.
      This subseries is divided into the following categories: Arthur Brodkin (1975-1984), General Files (1948-1980), Institutes (1955-1979), National Services (1954-1967), Study Committee (1959, 1968-1977), and Oliver Winkler (1932-1981). With the exception of Institutes, which is chronological, the files are arranged alphabetically.
      JWB's Health and Physical Education Department sponsored "... training programs and institutes to enrich the scope of Center health, physical education, and recreation programs, [recruited] Jewish youth for careers in Center health, physical education, and recreation work, and [provided] consultation to Centers on the construction of adequate health and physical education facilities. The department also [assisted] in coordinating inter-city tournaments and leagues which provide opportunities for young people to broaden their Jewish association."9
      This material includes files maintained by Arthur Brodkin, who helped to fill health and physical education positions at JCCs. The Brodkin files contain application forms and requests for jobs, and thus provide information on individuals employed in health and physical education positions at JCCs and camps. The General files include documents maintained by Oliver Winkler and Michael Rand, both of whom served as Health and Physical Education consultants. Found here are files on a variety of sports and health-related topics, such as Olympic games, golf, volleyball, wrestling, swimming, tennis, track and field programs, and programming for pre-school children, the handicapped, and older adults. Material on health and sex education and on smoking programs can also be found here, as can material on various health-related issues, such as heart disease. The National Services Files include basketball and handball tournament material, as well as material on the People to People Basketball program in Mexico, and items documenting JWB's participation in the Conference for National Cooperation in Aquatics (NCA.) The Study Committee material reflects the committee's efforts to assess and evaluate JWB's Health and Physical Education programs and to develop recommendations for the improvement of services. (Committee reports are included here.) Finally, Oliver Winkler's files include materials documenting interactions with other organizations, as well as consultation studies on communities and evaluations of programs. The subseries consists of correspondence, application forms, minutes, annual reports, brochures, surveys, questionnaires, studies, rules and regulations, flyers, lists, proclamations, press releases, forms, schedules, speeches, clippings and photographs, which are located in the Audio-Visual Materials Subgroup.
      9 "An Overview: JWB's Programs and Services," Dan Morris and Martin Halpern, undated, p. 42, I-337, NJWB, American Jewish Historical Society
      Related Materials: Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series A: Program Services/Subseries 1: Camping Services.
      Note: JWB Miscellaneous Box 6 is located at end of entire collection. The material relates to Oliver Winkler Files.
    - Subseries 4: Jewish Book Council, 1922-1985 (bulk 1940-1980); 13.67 linear feet.
      This subseries has been arranged into the following categories: Jewish Book Annual (1968-1980), Jewish Book Awards (1977-1985), Jewish Books in Review (1982-1984), Jewish Book World (1983-1984), General Files (1924-1925, 1939-1985), and Publications (1922-1976). Arranged chronologically, with exception of Jewish Book Annual and Publications, which are arranged alphabetically.
      In 1944 JWB became a sponsor and coordinator of the Jewish Book Council, which had originally been founded, in 1925, as Jewish Book Week and expanded through the following years.10 The Book Council's objectives were the stimulation of an abiding zeal for knowledge among young and old; the development of a Jewish cultural atmosphere in homes; the enrichment of educational programs of clubs, study circles and discussion groups; and the enlargement of book collections in institutional libraries, reading rooms, and private homes.11
      This subseries documents JWB's activities on behalf of the Book Council.
      Included here is material on the publications Jewish Book Annual and Jewish Book World, as well as various other publications, such as scripts for The Eternal Light, a radio show presented by NBC for the Jewish Theological Seminary of America, and plays on Jewish themes. Jewish book awards were given for books in such subjects as fiction, history, children's literature, and the holocaust; these files document the process by which award recipients were selected, and also provide biographical information on the winners themselves. Materials include certificates, correspondence, forms, clippings, bibliographies, awards, books, lists, minutes, reviews, questionnaires, plays, scripts, bulletins, newsletters, speeches, reports, articles, brochures, surveys, studies, proposals and photographs, which can be found in the Audio-Visual Materials Subgroup.
      10 Steinbach, A. Alan. JWB Jewish Book Council: Its History and Program. New York: JWB Jewish Book Council
      11 Goodman, Philip. "Report of the Jewish Book Council of America," undated, I-337, NJWB, American Jewish Historical Society
      Restrictions: Some of the General files are fragile.
      Note: JWB Miscellaneous Boxes 6 and 7 are located at end of entire collection. The material relates to General Files.
    - Subseries 5: Jewish Media Service, 1973-1984; 11.5 linear feet.
      This subseries is arranged as follows: General Files (1973-1984), Geographic Files (1973-1984), Harry Kosansky Files (1977-1984), and Subject Files (1974-1981). Arranged alphabetically.
      JWB became a primary sponsor of the Media Service in 1978, as did the Council of Jewish Federations and National United Jewish Appeal. (The Jewish Media Service was originally founded in 1973 by the Institute for Jewish Life, which operated under a mandate from the Council of Jewish Federations.) The Media Service evaluated and provided consultation and referral on media materials, distributed films and provided a central purchasing exchange for the purchase of equipment and films or videos. Further, the Media Service assisted communities in establishing media centers and conducted workshops on the use of media, as well as developing supplementary materials such as discussion guides. Finally, the Media Service consulted filmmakers and video producers, and published Medium, a Jewish media review.12
      The General files document the interaction of the Jewish Media Service with other Jewish organizations. Material on the Media Service's workshops and other programs can be found here, as can studies on the use of media in the promotion and support of Jewish culture. The Geographic files provide descriptions of Jewish film festivals, and other projects developed by organizations around the country, and also include files on activities in countries such as Canada, England, France, and South Africa. Also included are the files of Harry Kosansky, who, in his role as director of Program Development Services, oversaw the Jewish Media Service; this material documents the administration of the Media Service. Subject files contain descriptions of films in the Media Service's databank, on such topics as Arab-Israel conflict, American Jewish History, the Bible, parenting and Soviet Jewry. Material consists of correspondence, receipts, listings, scripts, programs, speeches, studies, brochures, forms, schedules, clippings, minutes, photographs, and phonograph records (which are located in the Audio-Visual Materials Subgroup.)
      12 The Jewish Media Service/JWB: Five Years of Service, 1983, I-337, NJWB, American Jewish Historical Society
      Related Materials: Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series B: Field Services/Subseries 6: Regional Area Offices/Boston Office.
    - Subseries 6: Jewish Music Council, 1923-1979; 12.5 linear feet.
      This series has been arranged into the following categories: Commission on JWB's Role in Jewish Cultural Programming (1969-1972), General Files (1923-1979), Geographic Files (1968-1981, 1973), Jewish Music and Composers (1937-1976), and Subject Files (1948-1973). Arranged alphabetically. (Jewish Music and Composers arranged chronologically.)
      This subseries documents the activities and functions of the Jewish Music Council, which was founded in 1944. The Music Council strove to collect and preserve traditional Jewish music and to connect that heritage to the growing musical life in America and in Israel.13 The files of the Commission on JWB's Role in Jewish Cultural Programming include background material on the commission, as well as its final results and recommendations. (The Commission recommended establishing an American Jewish Academy of the Cultural Arts, a Jewish Cultural Mass Media library and archive, and an American Jewish Cultural Center.) The General files contain indices and lists of Jewish music, Music Council budget, Biennial and committee materials, scripts for radio and television programs, and music and play scripts. In addition, the development of the Jewish Music Notes publication is documented here. The Geographic files document the Music Council's interactions with JCCs, synagogues, and temples, musical groups, orchestras, and other organizations. This material consists mainly of requests for information and materials from the Music Council, and illustrates the musical activities of Jewish organizations around the country. Finally, the subject files include music festival program material and materials for Israel's 25th anniversary. (Material related to the governance of the Music Council is also included here.) The material consists of correspondence, application forms, minutes, annual reports, brochures, surveys, questionnaires, sheet music, scripts, plays, studies, rules and regulations, flyers, lists, proclamations, press releases, forms, schedules, speeches, clippings and photographs, which are located in the Audio-Visual Materials Subgroup.
      13 Heskes, Irene. The National Jewish Music Council Celebrates its 25th Anniversary. I-337, NJWB, American Jewish Historical Society
      Related Materials: Subgroup I: Governance/Series C: Central Records Center/Subseries 6: National Services (Playwriting Contest Material); Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series E: Jewish Education Programs/Subseries 4: Jewish Educational and Cultural Programming.
    - Subseries 7: Lecture Bureau, 1904-1986 (bulk 1950-1980); 20.75 linear feet.
      This subseries has been organized into the following subsubseries: Artists Files (1947-1985), Calendars (1977-1985), Contracts (1977-1979, 1981-1983), Correspondence (1972-1981), General Files (1946-1977), Historical Files (1937-1964), Lecturer Files (1944-1986), Photograph Exhibits (1904-1986), Reports (1942-1977), and Sponsoring Organization Cards (1982-1984). Arranged alphabetically and chronologically.
      The Lecture Bureau made available to the various affiliated organizations that were interested artists and lecturers from around the world. These people included professors, historians, authors, rabbis, and holocaust survivors. Many of the lecturers and artists approached the JWB to be listed in their brochure. Other, more famous, people were asked by the JWB to join. Some of those asked were Gene Autry, Benjamin Spock, Arthur Miller, Adlai Stevenson, several US Senators, and Eleanor Roosevelt. With the exception of Benjamin Spock they all refused. A few of the artists who performed for the Lecture Bureau were Joey Adams, Terry Saunders with Norman Atkins, Herschel, Jack, and Sam Bernardi, Lillian Lux, Paddy Chayefsky, and Howard da Silva.
      The subseries describes the individuals and groups who performed for the Lecture Bureau, what kind of production was given, and the details of the contracts between the individuals and JWB.
      The material consists of photographs, negatives, slides, vinyl records and audio tapes (all located in Audio/Visual Materials Subgroup), correspondence, programs, pamphlets, calendars, confirmation of booking forms, confirmation of film-rental orders, receipts, contracts, newspaper clippings, spreadsheets, memoranda, press releases, book jackets, catalogs, condition reports, organization booking reminders and reports, sponsor cards and sequence plans.
      Related Material: Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series E: Jewish Education Programs/Subseries 4: Jewish Educational and Cultural Programming.
    - Subseries 8: Nursery School, 1945-1956; 2 linear feet.
      This subseries reflects the number of JCCs that had pre-schools, and highlights their programs and the experience of the teachers. Also indicated are the types of facilities available. The subseries consists of correspondence, memoranda, questionnaires, and pamphlets.
    - Subseries 9: Older Adults, 1943-1956; 2 linear feet.
      These records demonstrate the functions of programming for Older Adults including summer activities, radio scripts, studies and the problems that occurred. The material consists of correspondence, memoranda, program aids, pamphlets, and minutes.
    - Subseries 10: Program Development and Research Services, 1921-1988 (bulk 1935-1980); 54 linear feet.
      This subseries has been arranged as follows: S. Morton Altman Files (1947-1980; bulk 1970-1979), Steve Doochin Files (1977-1985), Miriam Ephraim Files (1921-1965), General Files (1945-1971), Edward Kagen Files (1974-1979), Harry Kosansky Files (1975-1983), Dan Morris Files (1975-1983), Steven Rod Files (1963, 1969-1976), Leonard Rubin Files (1977-1983), and Barry Shrage Files (1977-1979). Arranged alphabetically and chronologically.
      JWB understood that one of its chief functions was to define the needs of the JCCs and YMHAs and help them meet those needs. Therefore:
      "JWB has instituted approaches to the testing and development of new Center programs. It is concerned with the improvement of practice through the utilization of research, demonstration projects and training programs with the objective of encouraging Centers to focus on the achievement of Jewish communal objectives as well as to deal with current communal concerns."14
      S. Morton Altman was Associate Director of Program Development and Research Services and Director of Florence G. Heller - JWB Research Center. His materials consist of adolescent and youth studies, elderly programs, fiscal information for the Heller Research Center, statistical analysis of JCCs, and staffing issues.
      Miriam Ephraim was director of Program Services from 1950-1965. Her materials include annual reports of Program Services, work plans of various departments within Program Services, and a description of the Central Jewish Institute.
      Harry Kosansky was Director of Program Development and Research Services and JWB staff liaison to Florence Heller - JWB Research Center. His materials include community files, management and development of the Program Services Department, the Holocaust project, and the Russian resettlement.
      Dan Morris was Director of Program Development and Research Services. His materials consist of the reorganization of JWB during the 1970's, the social work function of the JCC, how JCCs coped with the economic problems of the early 1970's, and the International Training Project.
      Steven Rod was a Program Development Associate. His materials include camping services, college youth programs, and the "Teen clip 'n ship" system.
      Leonard Rubin was Director and Executive Director of Program Services. His materials include community services, the Holocaust project, Large City Center Executives Seminar, and the Soviet Jewry Acculturation project.
      The records consist of studies, correspondence, surveys, reports, letters, memoranda, lists, minutes, financial statements, proposals, newspaper clippings, articles, questionnaires, brochures, newsletters, telexes, photographs (located in Audio/Visual Materials Subgroup), publications, journals, pamphlets, speeches, evaluations, musical scores, plans, and policies.
      14 Untitled JWB Program Development and Research Services document, undated, I-337 NJWB, American Jewish Historical Society.
      Restrictions: Some material in Leonard Rubin Files is restricted due to subject matter.
      Note: JWB Miscellaneous Box 7 is located at end of entire collection. The material relates to the Miriam Ephraim Files.
    - Subseries 11: Publications, 1919-1976 (bulk 1945-1960); 13.5 linear feet.
      This subseries is comprised of the following subsubseries: Correspondence (1928-1966), Jewish Community Center Program Aids (JCCPA) (1940-1972), JCCPA: Correspondence (1942-1943, 1945-1953, 1955-1956), JCCPA: "To the Executive" (1944-1957), JWB Publications (1919-1976), JWB Publications: Inner Circle (1968-1972), JWB Publications: JWB Associates Newsletter (1966-1970), JWB Publications: Jewish History (1945-1976), and War Effort (1942-1944). Arranged alphabetically and chronologically.
      The subseries consists of the records and publications from the Publications Department. The publications included are holiday manuals, "Jewish Thoughts, 1919", ceremonial articles, bibliographies, plays, Program Aids, annual reports, "Jewish Center Songster", and "To the Executive".
      "To the Executive" was a kit sent to Center Executives and was used to supplement the materials from the Program Aids and contained current up-to-date information on holidays and activities.
      Of special interest are the materials pertaining to the 1976 Bicentennial Exhibit sponsored by the American Jewish Historical Society and JWB (JWB Publications: Jewish History), a programming source book dedicated in 1952 to Isaac Loeb Peretz including stories, poems, and essays written by Peretz himself (Jewish Community Center Program Aids), and the Selected Writings of Miriam R. Ephraim, 1966 written as a tribute to her after her retirement in 1965 (JWB Publications).